Developers before Docker and containers were like cavemen.
Dockerとコンテナ以前の時代に生きていた開発者は、まるで原始人と変わりませんでした。
When starting a new job, they'd spend the whole day setting up their development environment.
新しい会社に入社すると、開発環境の設定に一日中苦労していました。
Updating the development environment always broke something, so we prayed it wouldn't.
開発環境をアップデートすると、いつも何かが壊れるので、そうならないように必死で祈ったりもしました。
And when I tried to run my code on the server,
そして、自分が書いたコードをサーバーコンピュータに送って実行しようとすると、
the computer would crash or explode, so we even performed rituals before deploying.
コンピュータがエラーを起こして爆発したり、そんなことが多かったので、デプロイ前に祈祷したりもしました。
But after Docker and containers came along, that's mostly gone.
しかし、Dockerとコンテナが登場してからは、この面倒な作業がほとんどなくなりました。
That's probably why Docker has been the most used tool for developers for years.
そのためか、開発者が最もよく使うツール1位を毎年Dockerが占めています。
And these days, whether you're looking at a coding book or downloading a deep learning model online,
また最近では、プログラミングの本を見ようとしても、あるいはインターネットでディープラーニングモデルをダウンロードして動かそうとしても、
you often see Docker commands first.
Dockerのコマンドから表示されることが多いです。
So, what is Docker? It's an OS-level virtualization technology based on Linux containers.
さて、Dockerとは何かというと、Linuxコンテナを基盤に作られたOSレベルの仮想化技術ですが、
If I explain it like that, you'll all click the back button, so let's try to understand it easily.
こんな説明をすると皆、ブラウザバックしてしまうので、簡単に理解してみましょう。
Let's say you messed up while coding and opened a fried chicken restaurant in Seoul.
皆さんがプログラミングで失敗して、ソウルにチキン屋をオープンしたとしましょう。
And it does well, so you want to open a branch in Busan.
それがうまくいって、今度は釜山に支店を出したいとします。
How would you operate the Busan branch?
では、釜山支店はどう運営しますか？
The easiest way is to just send your recipe and tell them to follow it exactly.
一番簡単なのは、自分が使っていたレシピだけを送って、これをそのまま真似するように指示することです。
You could do that, but it would be a disaster.
それでもいいかもしれませんが、それでは人生も台無しになります。
The kitchen facilities, tools, and ingredients in Busan are all different from Seoul, which means
釜山とソウルでは、厨房設備も違うし、道具も違うし、材料も違うとなると、
there will be a lot of problems in the cooking process.
調理過程で問題もたくさん発生するでしょう。
And the taste will be slightly different.
味も少し変わってしまうのは避けられません。
So, to run a business properly, you'd prepare
だから、きちんと商売をするためには、皆さんがソウルで使っていた、
all the ingredients and recipes you used in Seoul like a meal kit and send them to Busan.
材料やレシピなどを全部ミールキットのように準備して、それを釜山に送ります。
Then in Busan, they can just heat it up and serve it.
そして釜山では、これを温めるだけで運営できるようにすればいいのです。
Most big franchise chicken restaurants operate like this, and it's the same when developing software.
大手のフランチャイズチキン店は、全てこのようなやり方をしていますが、開発も同じです。
I often need to run the same code on different computers.
同じコードを、それぞれ異なるコンピュータで実行する必要がある場合が多いのですが、
But if the code runs fine on my computer, and I just send it to another computer and try to run it,
自分のコンピュータでコードがうまく動いたからといって、これを他のコンピュータにそのまま送って実行すると、
it often results in a disaster.
大惨事がよく起こります。
Each computer has a different OS and different versions of the default programs installed.
コンピュータごとにOSも違うし、インストールされている基本プログラムのバージョンも違うからです。
If you don't want that, prepare the same OS and programs that you use,
それが嫌なら、皆さんが使っていたOSやプログラムなどを全部同じように準備した上で、
and then put your code on it and run it there.
その上にコードを入れて、その上で実行すればいいのです。
To do this, we used to use VMs.
このために昔は、VMというものを使っていました。
It's about installing another OS on top of an existing OS, but it's very heavy and doesn't perform well.
あるOSの上に別のOSをインストールするものですが、非常に重く、性能も良くないので、
So, these days we use Docker and containers instead.
最近は、その代わりにDockerとコンテナを使います。
With Docker, you can create a code meal kit.
Dockerを使うと、コードのミールキットのようなものを作ることができます。
You can put everything in it: the OS, SDK, required programs, libraries, and code.
そこにOS、SDK、必要なプログラム、ライブラリ、コードなどを全部入れることができます。
And with Docker, you can easily run the meal kit with just a click.
そして、Dockerを使うと、そのミールキットをボタン一つで簡単に実行することもできます。
So, Docker is basically just a simple program that creates and runs code meal kits.
だからDockerは、簡単に言うと、コードのミールキットを作って実行してくれる簡単なプログラムに過ぎません。
And by the way, there is a virtual computer that runs the meal kit,
ちなみに、ミールキットを実行している仮想コンピュータがありますが、
and cool developers call this a container.
これをかっこいい開発者の言葉でコンテナと呼びます。
But it's hard to understand just by talking, so let's take a quick look at how to use it.
ただ言葉で説明するだけでは理解が難しいので、どのように使うのか少しだけ試してみましょう。
To create a meal kit, you need a file.
ミールキットをどのように作るかというと、ファイルが一つ必要です。
It's called a Dockerfile.
Dockerfileというものが必要です。
You write down what OS to use, what programs, libraries, and SDKs to install,
ここに、どのOSを使うのか、どのプログラムやライブラリ、SDKをインストールするのか、
and how to run the code in it.
そして、どのコードをどのように実行するのかを記述できます。
Then, with just one command, it's packaged up.
その後、コマンドを一つ入力すればパッケージングが完了します。
And then you can run this meal kit with a single click.
そして、クリック一回でこのミールキットを実行できます。
Then the code inside will run.
そうすると、中に入っていたコードが実行されるでしょう。
And it will run your code stably on the OS and working environment that you set in the Dockerfile.
しかし、皆さんがDockerfileで設定した、そのOSと作業環境、ライブラリの上で、
The OS and the working environment, the library,
自分のコードを安定的に実行してくれます。
That's it. That's how you use Docker and containers.
これがDockerとコンテナの使い方、終わりです。
You've learned it all.
もう全部学びました。
After Docker and containers were discovered, developers started doing all sorts of amazing things with them.
Dockerとコンテナが発見されてから、開発者たちもこれを使って、いろいろな面白いことを始めました。
Because meal kits made deployment much easier, the way servers are developed these days is that
ミールキットのおかげで、デプロイなども非常に簡単になったので、最近はどのようにサーバーを開発するかというと、
in the past, server functions were all crammed into one program,
以前は、サーバー機能を一つのプログラムの中に全部詰め込んでいましたが、
but now it's split into multiple programs.
今は、それを分割して複数のプログラムに分けています。
This is called MSA and it's the bread and butter of the backend these days.
これをMSAと言いますが、最近のバックエンドの生命線となっています。
And because building, testing, and deploying programs
そして、プログラムをビルドし、テストし、デプロイする作業が、
has become easy enough for even elementary school kids to do, thanks to Docker,
Dockerのおかげで、小学生でもできる程度になったので、
more and more places are starting to adopt automatic deployment.
自動デプロイなどを導入し始める企業が非常に多くなりました。
And with Docker, you can easily install
そして、Dockerを使うと、欲しいプログラムを
the program you want on the version and OS you want, and even cleanly remove it.
欲しいバージョン、そして欲しいOSの上に非常に簡単にインストールし、きれいに削除までできるので、
This has led to the emergence of developers with germophobia who don't want to install anything on their local computers.
自分のローカルコンピュータに何かをインストールするのが嫌な潔癖症の開発者が現れ始めました。
If you're curious about what Docker really is, it's nothing special.
Dockerの実体が気になれば、実は大したことではなく、
There was originally a lightweight virtualization technology in Linux itself.
Linux自体に、元々軽い仮想化技術のようなものがあったのですが、
Using that, you can create something called a container.
これを使うとコンテナというものを作ることができます。
Just think of it as a virtual computer.
ただの仮想コンピュータだと思えばいいでしょう。
There are programs that help ordinary people create them easily.
これを一般の人でも簡単に作れるように手助けしてくれるプログラムのようなものもあります。
Docker is just a tool that makes it easy for even a dog to use these things.
しかし、これらを犬でも簡単に使えるように作ったのが、Dockerというツールに過ぎません。
And by the way, there are some alternatives to Docker.
なので、ちなみにDockerの代わりに使える代替品もいくつかあります。
Or you can even run Linux containers directly without Docker.
あるいは、Dockerなしで直接Linuxコンテナを起動することも可能です。
Of course, there are downsides.
当然、デメリットもあります。
You have to take care of new security issues.
新しいセキュリティの問題にも注意しなければなりませんし、
If you have a lot of containers, you need people to manage them.
コンテナが増えれば、それを管理する人員も必要になります。
And server costs can be higher than you think at the beginning.
サーバー費用なども、初期段階では思ったよりかかるでしょう。
Also, when you need to store data permanently and stably, containers might not be a good idea.
そして、何かデータを永続的に安定して保存する必要がある場合は、コンテナはあまり適していないかもしれません。
But the most important thing is that the learning curve for coding beginners has become steeper.
しかし、最も重要なのは、プログラミング初心者の学習曲線が厳しくなったということです。
Because Docker is so popular, some lectures and books make you set up Docker from the start of your coding journey.
Dockerが良いからといって、プログラミング入門時にDockerの設定からさせる講義や本もありますが、
To give you an analogy of this,
そのようなやり方を例えて言うと、
it's like learning to cook by going to a pre-made kitchen set,
料理を学ぶと言いながら、人が全部作ったセットに行って、
taking out a chicken meal kit, opening it, and frying it.
チキンミールキットを持ってきて、このように開けて揚げてみる程度のことです。
If you want to do only that until you die, then go ahead.
皆さんがそれだけやって満足なら、それでも構いませんが、
But if you want to create your own chicken recipe, make your own meal kit, and open your own branch,
後々、自分だけのチキン料理を作って、自分だけのミールキットも作って、自分だけの支店も出したいと思うなら、
it's also important to try cooking on your own without relying on someone else's meal kit.
他人のミールキットなどに頼らず、自分で直接料理をしてみることも重要です。
So, when you're starting to code, you should fight with your own computer directly without Docker, like a UFC match.
つまり、プログラミング入門をする際は、Dockerの助けなしに、自分のコンピュータと直接戦って、UFCを一度やってみろということです。
That experience is necessary for you to confidently write Dockerfiles, build, and deploy later on.
そのような経験があってこそ、後で自信を持ってDockerfileを作成し、このようにビルドしてデプロイできるようになります。
But this isn't a time to learn coding,
しかし、今はプログラミングを学ぶ時間ではないので、
so I'll stop with the nagging since we are here to learn Docker, a simple tool.
Dockerという簡単なツールを学ぶ時間なので、お説教はここまでにします。
Now, I've mainly prepared how to use Docker well on your own,
これからは、Dockerを一人で使いこなせるようになる方法を中心に準備してきたので、
so you can learn these things.
これらを学んでいただければと思います。
And later, let's also learn how to use Docker Compose and orchestration tools.
そして、後でDocker Composeとオーケストレーションツールの使い方まで見ていきましょう。